Bastián González-Bustamante

DPhil (PhD) Programme · University of Oxford

St Hilda's College, Cowley Place, Oxford OX4 1DY, UK

Summary_

I am completing my DPhil (PhD) dissertation in the Department of Politics and International Relations and St Hilda's College at the University of Oxford, United Kingdom. I am currently based in Oxford, working on my research. Furthermore, I am an Instructor Professor in the Management and Public Policies Department at the Faculty of Administration and Economics at the Universidad de Santiago de Chile.

Before starting the DPhil, in October 2019, I earned an MA (1st) in Political Science and a BA (2:1) in Government, both from the Universidad de Chile. Moreover, I served as a lecturer at the Universidad de Chile and a consultant for the United Nations Development Programme (UNDP).

My doctoral research is supervised by Professor Petra Schleiter and focuses on cabinets' stability in Latin American presidential democracies. In my DPhil project, I combine the principal-agent theory elements to evaluate the actors' incentives and strategies in presidential systems. My empirical strategy employs propensity scores and matching methods, competing risks models, and IV estimations. My research is funded by the Chilean National Agency for Research and Development and St Hilda's College.

Education

University of Oxford Oxford, UK

DPhil (PhD) in Politics 2019 - ongoing

Professor Petra Schleiter (Supervisor)

Universidad de Chile Santiago, Chile 2010 - 2013

MA in Political Science Highest Distinction (1st, First-class honours)

Universidad de Chile Santiago, Chile

BA in Government 2004 - 2009

Distinction (2:1, Second-class honours, upper division)

Universidad de Chile Santiago, Chile

BPS in Public Administration 2004 - 2009

Distinction (2:1, Second-class honours, upper division)

Relevant Employment_

Universidad de Santiago de Chile Santiago, Chile

Instructor Professor 2019 - on leave

Management and Public Policies Department, Faculty of Administration and Economics

Universidad de Santiago de Chile Santiago, Chile

Adjunct Professor 2014 - 2018

Management and Public Policies Department, Faculty of Administration and Economics

United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) Santiago, Chile

Consultant 2016 - 2017

Democratic Governance Programme

Universidad de Chile Santiago, Chile

2013 - 2016

School of Government and Public Management, Institute of Public Affairs

Peer-Reviewed Articles

SOCIAL SCIENCES CITATION INDEX (WOS-ISI/SCCI)

- 7. Orchard, X., & González-Bustamante, B. (*forthcoming*). Power Hierarchies and Visibility in the News: Exploring Determinants of Politicians' Presence and Prominence in the Chilean Press (1991-2019). *The International Journal of Press/Politics*.
- 6. Cuevas, C. *et al.* (*forthcoming*). Public Service Motivation Among Chilean Public Employees. *Revista del CLAD Reforma y Democracia*, 80. [IN SPANISH]. SOCARXIV: 10.31235/osf.io/p963q
- 5. González-Bustamante, B. (2021). Evolution and Early Government Responses to COVID-19 in South America. *World Development*, 137, 105180. DOI: 10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105180
- 4. González-Bustamante, B. (2020). The Politics-Administration Dichotomy: A Case Study of the Chilean Executive During the Democratic Post-Transition. *Bulletin of Latin American Research*, *39*(5), 582–597. DOI: 10.1111/blar.13044
- 3. González-Bustamante, B., Carvajal, A., & González, A. (2020). Determinants of E-Government in the Municipalities: Evidence from the Chilean Case. *Gestión y Política Pública, XXIX*(1), 97–129. [IN SPANISH]. DOI: 10.29265/gypp.v29i1.658. SocARXIV: 10.31235/osf.io/fze3x
- 2. González-Bustamante, B. (2019). Gaps, Representation, and Elite-Mass Congruence in Chile and Uruguay. *Convergencia. Revista de Ciencias Sociales*, 80, 1–27. [IN SPANISH]. DOI: 10.29101/crcs.v26i80.11097. URL: www.redalyc.org. SocARXIV: 10.31235/osf.io/cqym8
- 1. González-Bustamante, B., & Garrido-Vergara, L. (2018). Socialization, Trajectories and Post-Career of Ministers in Chile, 1990-2010. *Política y Gobierno, XXV*(1), 31–64. [IN SPANISH]. URL: www.politicaygobierno.cide.edu

SCOPUS & EMERGING SOURCES CITATION INDEX (WOS-ISI/ESCI)

- 8. González-Bustamante, B., Astete, M., & Orvenes, B. (2020). Senior Public Managers: A Novel Dataset on Members of the Chilean Civil Service. *Revista de Gestión Pública, IX*(2), 151–169. [IN SPANISH AND ENGLISH]. DOI: 10.22370/rgp.2020.9.2.2920. SocARXIV: 10.31235/osf.io/vshcz
- 7. Olivares, A. *et al.* (2020). New Challenges, Approaches, and Perspectives in the Study of Political Elites. *Iberoamericana, XX*(74), 229–259. [IN SPANISH]. DOI: 10.18441/ibam.20.2020.74.229-259. SocARXIV: 10.31235/osf.io/syqu4
- 6. Maillet, A., González-Bustamante, B., & Olivares, A. (2019). Public-Private Circulation and the Revolving Door in the Chilean Executive Branch (2000-2014). *Latin American Business Review, 20*(4), 367–387. DOI: 10.1080/10978526.2019.1652099
- 5. Barría, D., González-Bustamante, B., & Cisternas, C. (2019). The Literature on Open Government in Spanish. Analysis of the Dynamics of Production and Citation. *Nóesis. Revista de Ciencias Sociales y Humanidades,* 28(56), 22–42. [IN SPANISH]. DOI: 10.20983/noesis.2019.2.3
- 4. Del Valle, N., & González-Bustamante, B. (2018). Political Agenda, Journalism and Digital Media in Chile: Research Notes on Media Pluralism. *Perspectivas de la Comunicación, 11*(1), 291–326. [IN SPANISH]. URL: http://revistas.ufro.cl
- 3. González-Bustamante, B., & Olivares, A. (2016). Cabinet Turnover and Survival of Ministers in Chile During the Concertacion Governments (1990-2010). *Colombia Internacional*, 87, 81–108. [IN SPANISH]. DOI: 10.7440/colombiaint87.2016.04
- 2. González-Bustamante, B. et al. (2016). Civil Service in Chile, Analysis of Senior Civil Servants on the Top Rung of the Hierarchy (2003-13). Revista de Administração Pública, 50(1), 59–79. [IN SPANISH]. DOI: 10.1590/0034-7612145767
- 1. González-Bustamante, B., & Olivares, A. (2015). Undersecretaries Rotation in Chile: An Exploration of the Second Government Line, 1990-2014. *Revista de Gestión Pública, IV*(2), 151–190. [IN SPANISH]. DOI: 10.22370/rgp.2015.4.2.2230

SCIELO & LATINDEX

- 10. González-Bustamante, B., & Luci, F. (*forthcoming*). Political Elites in Latin America: Socialisation, Trajectories, and Capitals. Introduction. *Pléyade, Revista de Humanidades y Ciencias Sociales*, 28. [IN SPANISH]. SocARXIV: 10.31235/osf.io/wud59
- 9. González-Bustamante, B. (2016). Political, Economic, and Intellectual Elites: A Growing Research Agenda for Political Science. *Política, Revista de Ciencia Política*, 54(1), 7–17. [IN SPANISH]. URL: https://revistapolitica.uchile.cl
- 8. González-Bustamante, B., & Cisternas, C. (2016). Political Elites in the Chilean Legislative Branch: The Chamber of Deputies (1990-2014). *Política, Revista de Ciencia Política, 54*(1), 19–52. [IN SPANISH]. URL: https://revistapolitica.uchile.cl
- 7. González-Bustamante, B. (2015). Assessing Twitter as a Public Opinion Measure: An Exploration of the Bachelet's Arrival to the Chilean Presidential Campaign 2013. *Revista SAAP*, 9(1), 119–141. [IN SPANISH]. URL: http://ref.scielo.org
- 6. González-Bustamante, B. (2015). Electoral Success and Campaign Spending in Elections of Senators and Deputies in Chile 2013. *Políticas Públicas*, 8(1), 21–35. [IN SPANISH]. URL: www.revistas.usach.cl
- 5. González-Bustamante, B. (2014). Popular Election of Regional Councillors 2013. Performance of Political, Family, and Economic Capital in a New Electoral Arena in Chile. *Política, Revista de Ciencia Política, 52*(2), 49–91. [IN SPANISH]. URL: https://revistapolitica.uchile.cl
- 4. Olivares, A. *et al.* (2014). Think Tanks in the Cabinet: An Exploration of the Chilean Case (2006-2014). *Revista de Sociología*, 29, 37–54. [IN SPANISH]. DOI: 10.5354/0719-529X.2014.36177. URL: https://revistadesociologia.uchile.cl
- 3. González-Bustamante, B. (2013). Factors Affecting Access and Permanence of the Governmental Political Elite in Chile (1990-2010). *Política, Revista de Ciencia Política, 51*(1), 119–153. [IN SPANISH]. DOI: 10.5354/0716-1077.2013.27436cl. URL: https://revistapolitica.uchile.cl
- 2. González-Bustamante, B. (2013). The Study of the Elites in Chile: Theoretical and Methodological Approaches. *Intersticios Sociales*, 6, 1–20. [IN SPANISH]. URL: http://ref.scielo.org
- 1. González-Bustamante, B., & Henríquez, G. (2012). Digital Campaigns: Branding or Political Participation? *Más Poder Local*, 12, 32–39. [IN SPANISH]. URL: www.researchgate.net

Peer-Reviewed Edited Volumes _____

- 2. González-Bustamante, B., & Luci, F. (forthcoming). Political Elites in Latin America: Socialisation, Trajectories, and Capitals. Pléyade, Revista de Humanidades y Ciencias Sociales, 28. [IN SPANISH].
- 1. González-Bustamante, B. (2016). Political, Economic, and Intellectual Elites. *Política, Revista de Ciencia Política*, 54(1). [IN SPANISH]. URL: https://revistapolitica.uchile.cl

Book Chapters

- 13. González-Bustamante. B. (forthcoming). Quantitative Methods for Studying Elites: Practical Applications, Biases and Potential. In F. Robles, I. Nercesián & M. Serna (eds.), Elites económicas, Estado y dominación en América Latina: Cambios y continuidades en la época post COVID. Buenos Aires: Siglo XXI Editores. [IN SPANISH].
- 12. González-Bustamante, B. (2018). Civil Service Models in Latin America. In A. Farazmand (ed.), *Global Encyclopedia of Public Administration*, *Public Policy, and Governance*. Cham: Springer. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-319-20928-9_2699. SocARXIV: 10.31235/osf.io/mp4qd
- 11. González-Bustamante, B. (2018). Internet, Digital Social Networks Usage, and Participation in the Southern Cone. In P. Cottet (ed.), *Opinión Pública Contemporánea: Otras Posibilidades de Comprensión e Investigación*. Santiago: Social-Ediciones. [IN SPANISH]. DOI: 10.34720/2nd0-8t73

- 10. González-Bustamante, B., & Olivares, A. (2018). Governmental Political Elite in Chile: Ministers Survival (1990-2014). In A. Codato & F. Espinoza (eds.), *Las Élites en las Américas: Diferentes Perspectivas*. Curitiba: Editora da Universidade Federal do Paraná. [IN SPANISH]. URL: www.researchgate.net
- 9. González-Bustamante, B., & Barría, D. (2018). Expansion of the Public Sphere in Chile: Social Networks, Electoral Campaigns, and Digital Participation. In N. Del Valle (ed.), *Transformaciones de la Esfera Pública en Chile. Luchas Sociales, Espacio Público y Pluralismo Informativo*. Santiago: RIL Editores. [IN SPANISH]. SOCARXIV: 10.31235/osf.io/nkftb
- 8. Barría, D., González-Bustamante, B., & Araya, J. E. (2017). Electronic Democracy and Digital Participation: Advances and Challenges. In J. R. Gil-García, J. I. Criado & J. C. Téllez (eds.), *Tecnologías de Información y Comunicación en la Administración Pública: Conceptos, Enfoques, Aplicaciones y Resultados*. Mexico City: INFOTEC. [IN SPANISH]. URL: www.researchgate.net
- 7. González-Bustamante, B. (2016). Twitter Usage in Political Communication. In I. Crespo *et al.* (eds.), *Diccionario Enciclopédico de Comunicación Política*. Madrid: Centro de Estudios Políticos y Constitucionales. [IN SPANISH, 2ND EDITION].
- 6. González-Bustamante, B., & Sazo, D. (2016). Viral Campaign. In I. Crespo et al. (eds.), Diccionario Enciclopédico de Comunicación Política. Madrid: Centro de Estudios Políticos y Constitucionales. [IN SPANISH, 2ND EDITION].
- 5. González-Bustamante, B., & Sazo, D. (2016). Political Branding. In I. Crespo *et al.* (eds.), *Diccionario Enciclopédico de Comunicación Política*. Madrid: Centro de Estudios Políticos y Constitucionales. [IN SPANISH, 2ND EDITION].
- 4. González-Bustamante, B. (2014). New Media and Digital Politics: The Case of Chilean Primary Presidential Elections 2013. In G. Sibaja (ed.), *Nuevos Medios y Comunicación Política Digital*. San Jose: Fundación Educativa San Judas Tadeo. [IN SPANISH].
- 3. González-Bustamante, B. (2014). Digital Activism, Social Networks, and Brokerage. En S. Millaleo & P. Cárcamo (eds.), *Mediaciones del Sistema Político frente al Activismo Digital*. Santiago: Fundación Democracia y Desarrollo. [IN SPANISH]. URL: www.researchgate.net
- 2. González-Bustamante, B. (2014). Social Networks as a Tool for Political Engage: Twitter and the Public Opinion Concept. In O. Avilés *et al.* (eds.), *Práctica Política y Medios Digitales*. Santiago: Instituto Igualdad. [IN SPANISH].
- 1. González-Bustamante, B., & Henríquez, G. (2013). Chile: The Digital Campaign 2009-2010. In I. Crespo & J. del Rey (eds.), *Comunicación Política & Campañas Electorales en América Latina*. Buenos Aires: Editorial Biblos. [IN SPANISH].

Working Papers and Reviews

- 6. González-Bustamante, B. (2021). Sophistication, Participation, and Political Engagement in Latin America. *Tufte Working Papers*, 2, 1–21. [IN SPANISH]. SocARXIV: 10.31235/osf.io/r4pj8
- 5. González-Bustamante, B., & Cisternas, C. (2020). Applying ForceAtlas2, a Continuous Graph Layout Algorithm, to the Elites Study. *Tufte Working Papers*, 1, 1–15. [IN SPANISH]. SOCARXIV: 10.31235/osf.io/gxrkc
- 4. Maillet, A., González-Bustamante, B., & Olivares, A. (2016). Revolving Door. Analysis of Public-Private Circulation in Chile (2000-2014). *Serie Documentos de Trabajo PNUD-Desigualdad*, 7, 1–40. [IN SPANISH]. DOI: 10.13140/RG.2.2.25510.42566
- 3. González-Bustamante, B., & Olivares, A. (2016). Undersecretaries Rotation in the Chilean Cabinets (1990-2014). Observatório de elites políticas e sociais do Brasil. NUSP/UFPR, 3(5), 1–19. [IN PORTUGUESE]. URL: www.researchgate.net
- 2. González-Bustamante, B., & Soto, D. (2016). Pluralism in the Chilean Digital Mass Media, Exploratory Study of Key Cases. Serie Política, Gestión y Políticas Públicas, 2, 1–26. [IN SPANISH]. DOI: 10.13140/RG.2.2.33899.03362
- 1. González-Bustamante, B. (2015). Programas de Naciones Unidas para el Desarrollo (PNUD). (2014). Ciudadanía Política: Voz y Participación Ciudadana en América Latina. Buenos Aires: Siglo Veintiuno Editores. *Revista de Gestión Pública*, *IV*(1), 143–149. [IN SPANISH]. DOI: 10.22370/rgp.2015.4.1.2240

Relevant Teaching Experience _____

- School of Business, **Universidad Mayor**, Santiago, Chile
 - Machine Learning in Public Policy and Economics (workshop, Prof. Carla Cisternas), spring 2021
- Department of Politics and International Relations, **University of Oxford**, Oxford, UK
 - o Comparative Government (undergraduate tutorial, Prof. Petra Schleiter), Hilary 2020
- Faculty of Adminstration and Economics, **Universidad de Santiago**, Santiago, Chile
 - o Political Science I (undergraduate lecture), spring 2014, 2018, fall 2015-2019
 - o Political Science II (undergraduate lecture), spring 2015-2018
 - Econometrics for Public Policies (undergraduate lecture), fall 2018
 - o Workshop for Research Design (graduate seminar), spring 2017-2018
 - Research Methodology (undergraduate lecture), spring 2014-2015, fall 2015-2017
 - o Introduction to Quantitative Methods (undergraduate lecture), fall 2017
- School of Government and Public Management, Universidad de Chile, Santiago, Chile
 - o Study of Political Phenomena (undergraduate lecture), fall 2016
 - o Political Analysis (undergraduate lecture), fall 2014
 - o Elite Theory and Democracy (undergraduate lecture, Prof. Alejandro Olivares), spring 2013-2014

Honours & Awards _____

2022	St Hilda's College Travel Grant. Allowances for conference participation in the USA, £ 950	Oxford, UK
2022	SLAS Conference Grant. Travel support for the Society for Latin American Studies (SLAS) Annual Conference, £ 400	Bath, UK
2021	St Hilda's College Muriel Wise Fund and Book Grant . Research grant for the training of machine learning algorithms, DPhil (PhD) project data storage, and allowances for books, £ 530	Oxford, UK
2020	St Hilda's College Travel and Book Grants. Allowances for conference participation in Portugal and books, £ 745	Oxford, UK
2019	Becas Chile Doctoral Scholarship Abroad. Tuition fees, transport and living expenses for pursuing a DPhil (PhD) at the University of Oxford (ANID/PFCHA/72200340), £ 160,000	Oxford, UK
2016	LASA Travel Grant . Travel support for the XXXIV International Congress of the Latin American Studies Association (LASA/40071), £ 400	New York, USA
2016	CESS Summer School Scholarship. Financial support for the Experimental Summer School Methods at the Nuffield-USACH Centre for Experimental Social Sciences (CESS), £ 200	Santiago, Chile
2015	ALACIP Methodological School Prize . Best methodological work at the Latin American Political Association School (ALACIP)	Lima, Peru
2015	ACCP Winter School Scholarship . Financial support for the Winter School in Methods and Data Analysis at the Universidad Católica de Uruguay, awarded by the Chilean Political Science Association (ACCP), £ 300	Montevideo, URY

2014	PUC Summer School Scholarship. Financial support for the Summer School in Mixed Methods at the Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile (PUC), £ 170	Santiago, Chile
2013	Comunicracia Prize . Best paper of the political communication area at the XI Argentinian Congress of Political Science (double-blind peer-review), £ 170	Parana, Argentina
2013	Highest Rating MA Dissertation. The highest rating and the congratulations from the jury at the Universidad de Chile	Santiago, Chile
2012	FONDECYT Thesis Writing Grant . Financial support for MA fieldwork (Prof. Gonzalo Delamaza, Supervisor, ANID/FONDECYT/1100877), £ 1,150	Santiago, Chile

Selected Conference Presentations _____

* Selection only from the last five years, complete list available on GitHub

Virtual	Latin American Studies Association (LASA)	2022
Bath, UK	Society for Latin American Studies (SLAS)	2022
Virtual	International Political Science Association (IPSA)	2021
Boston, USA	Latin American Studies Association (LASA)	2019
Santiago, Chile	Chilean Political Science Association (ACCP)	2018
Murcia, Spain	Latin American Association of Electoral Campaign Researchers (ALICE)	2018
Pucon, Chile	Chilean Political Science Association (ACCP)	2018
Montevideo, URY	Latin American Political Science Association (ALACIP)	2017

Peer Reviewer & Expert _____

- Varieties of Democracy Project, University of Gothenburg, Sweden, 2014, 2018-2020
- Global Academic Reputation Survey, Clarivate Analytics, USA, 2020
- Sectoral Commission for Research, Universidad de la República, Uruguay, 2016, 2018
- Times Higher Education World University Rankings, ELSEVIER, Netherlands, 2018-2019, 2022
- Reviewer in WoS-ISI/SSCI/ESCI & Scopus journals, since 2013
- Reviewer in SciELO & LATINDEX journals, since 2013

Languages & Software _____

Languages Spanish (native speaker), English (fluent), Portuguese (advanced reading skills), French (elemental reading skills)

Programming & R, Python, Stata, SPSS/PSPP, Gephi, UCINET, NetDraw, Tosmana, Fuzzy-Sets, ArcGIS, ATLAS.ti, **Software** EndNote, Zotero, HPOP, LTEX, BibTEX, JabRef, MS Office, WordPress, Moodle, HTML, CSS, XHTML

Typed in X_{\exists} ETeX with hyperlinks. References upon request. lacktriangle Download the latest version in English or Spanish.